A Guide to the paper of Harold J. Morowitz, 1927 -
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
The papers of Harold J. Morowitz 1927 -
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
morowitz001
The collection comprises 15 boxes totaling 5 cubic feet ( 7.5 linear feet)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This is an open collection originally dontated by Mr. Morowitz in 1995
Biographical Information
Dr. Harold J. Morowitz is a biophysicist and Robinson Professor in Biology and Natural Philosophy at George Mason University. He was born in Poughkeepsie, N.Y. on December 4, 1927. Dr. Morowitz earned his B.S. in Physics and Philosophy at in 1947, his M.S. in Physics in 1950 and his Ph.D. in 1951 at Yale University. From 1951 to 1953 he was a physicist at the National Bureau of Standards. He was on the staff of the National Heart Institute from 1953 to 1955, before joining the faculty of Yale Institute in 1955. At Yale University, Dr. Morowitz was as an Assistant Professor from 1955 to 1960, an Associate Professor of biophysics from 1960 to 1967 and a Professor of Molecular biophysics and biochemistry from 1967 to 1988. He was Master of Pierson College from 1981 to 1986. He joined the faculty of George mason University in 1988 as a Robinson Professor and was Director of the Krasnow Institute of Advanced Study from 1993 to 1998
Scope and Content
The Morowitz Manuscript Collection includes the following: Energy Flow in Biological Systems: draft copy of the book, including chapter and appendix notes, illustrations, calculations for mathematical operations, and correspondence between the author and his editor; The Beginnings of Cellular Life: draft copy of the work, including the index and notes; The Facts of Life: draft copy of the book, with the "author's copy," and the original artwork for the illustrations; Correspondence with scientists in his and allied fields of study (i.e. Efraim Racker, Albert Einstein, Dr. Peter Mitchell, R.N. Robertson, S.L. Slater) as well as publications of some of these scientists. Archival materials (i.e., working papers, correspondence, etc.) pertaining to his academic career; and some original poetry written by Morowitz.
Arrangement
By subject
Contents List
- Morowitz Collection
  - [Photos], folder 1 (Box box 1)
  - [Petition to Adlai Stevenson from Yale Scientists and Related correspondence 1956 - 1957, folder 2 (Box box 1)
    Hydrogen bomb
  - Some calculations, folder 3 (Box box 1)
  - [hand written draft] Chapters V and VI December 1966, folder 4 (Box box 1)
    Also included letter a National Bureau of Standards Chemist regarding data Dr. Morowitz requested
  - [draft] Chapter 3, folder 5 (Box box 1)
  - Calculations Chapter IV [draft], folder 6 (Box box 1)
  - [Draft: Energy Flow in Biological Systems; An Inquiry Into Biological Organization as a Problem in Thermal Physics], folder 7 (Box box 1)
  - A Thermodynamic Characterization of Self Reproduction [article 4/1964, folder 8 (Box box 1)
    written by Dr. Morowitz, published in Reviews of Modern Physics
  - Lipids 4/1965, 4/22/66, folder 9 (Box box 1)
    Included: Article by W. Groth on Photochemical Production of Some Organic Compounds Under Primitive Earth Conditions, Hand-Written Notes on Photochemistry In the Liquid and Solid State, Draft Chapter II, Letter of advisory comment 4/22/66, UM; article by Egbert G. Leigh, Jr, "On Relation Between the Productivity, Biomass, Diversity, and Stability of a Community", Letter of constructive Criticism from Robert MacArthur, Princeton University, Article by E.T. Jaynes, 5/15/57, "Information Theory and Statistical Mechanics
  - Appendix II, [Steady State Analysis of an Evolutionary Model System] [draft], folder 10 (Box box 1)
  - "Dr. Morowitz" [Notes, Correspondence] 4/7/67, 4/16/67 - 4/21/67, folder 1 (Box box 2)
    Charts for book, letters of suggestions from colleagues
  - "Harold" Notes [draft of introduction to book], folder 2 (Box box 2)
  - "Chapter IV', folder 3 (Box Box 2)
  - "Chapter III" draft, folder 4 (Box box 2)
  - "Chapter V" [draft], folder 5 (Box box 2)
  - "Notes for Chapter VI" Summer 1965, folder 6 (Box box 2)
    Included: Article by D. Scott, The determination and Use of Thermodynamic Data in Ecology, Second Draft of Table of Contents for Book
  - [Draft Beginnings of Cellular Life: Metabolism Recapitulates Biogenesis 12/18/91, folder 1 (Box box 3)
  - ["Beginnings of Cellular Life" First page proofs] 8/19/92, folder 2 (Box box 3)
  - [Drafts of Index for book "Beginnings of Cellular Life" ^/1992 and 11/12/92, folder 3 (Box box 3)
  - [draft from Oxford University Press of "Facts of Life" 3/19/93, folder 4 (Box box 3)
    includes Dr. Morowitz's opinion on when a fetus can be considered live.
  - ["Facts of Life": Author's Copy, folder 5 (Box box 3)
  - Photosynthesis, folder 1 (Box box 4)
    Includes: Draft article by Dr Morowitz (Yale) and Alan Bearden (university of California, Berkeley, "Photosynthetic Efficiency, A Misuse of Thermodynamics"; article by William Parson, "Thermodynamics of the Primary Reactions of Photosynthesis", article by Witt, Schlodder, Brettel, and Saygin, "Reaction Sequences from Light Absorption to the Cleavage of Water in Photosynthesis - Routes, Rates and Intermediates", article by Robert Knox, "Thermodynamics and the Primary Processes of Photosynthesis, article by R.S. Knox, "Conversion of Light into Free Energy
  - Salt Meeting [Halophic Bacteria] 8/6/92 -8/17/95, folder 2 (Box box 4)
    Dr. Morowitz had a NASA contract on the Viability of Halophilic Bacteria in Ancient Salt Deposits
  - NCAR [Bioinformatics] 7/9/90 - 3/9/98, folder 4 (Box box 4)
    includes data from Bioinformatics Workshop, 2/3/98 - 2/4/98
  - Publications [35 articles by Dr. Morowitz] 11/20/67 - 4/2001, folder 5 (Box box 4)
  - Frogs - Folder 1 [Workshop on Declining Amphibian Populations 2/19 - 20 1990] 11/2/89 - 8/1/98, folder 6 (Box box 4)
    Workshop correspondence and articles describing the decline of amphibians
  - Frogs - Folder 2 10/13/89 - 8/2/90, folder 7 (Box box 4)
  - Peace 2/19/60 - 9/19/60, folder 1 (Box box 5)
    correspondence regarding Professor Morowitz's interest in the National Peace Agency Act
  - [Back Contamination - Apollo 11 6/4/69, folder 2 (Box box 5)
  - Quastler, [Henry} 1957 - 1963, folder 3 (Box box 5)
  - Theoretical Biology Committee 10/12/67 - 5/20/70, folder 4 (A) (Box box 5)
  - Theoretical Biology Colloquium: Traverse City, MI 1968 11/23/64 - 9/17/68, folder 4(B) (Box box 5)
  - Biology Training for Apollo Astronauts 1/17/68 - 9/17/71, folder 5 (Box box 5)
    also included letter from American Type Culture Collection, 11/28/58
  - Medvedev [Russian scientist] 7/16/59 - 9/14/61, folder 6 (Box box 5)
  - Brownowski 1973, folder 7 (Box box 5)
  - A Germ of Truth [Manuscript], folder 8 (Box box 5)
  - Logue, Frank [Mayor New Haven CT] 8/26/76 - 9/27/76, folder 9 (Box box 5)
  - Thomas, Lewis 6/9/76, folder 10 (Box box 5)
  - Watson/Sinsheimer 6/29/61 - 7/14/61, folder 11 (Box box 5)
    letters of comment on his MS
  - Kendrew, John 11/15/61, folder 12 (Box box 5)
  - Gellman, Murray 1/23/67, folder 13 (Box box 5)
  - Sagan, Carl 1/10/69 - 6/17/71, folder 14 (Box box 5)
    editor of Icarus
  - Palade, George 5/4/70, folder 15 (Box box 5)
  - Mitchell, Peter 5/27/77, folder 16 (Box box 5)
  - [Nobel Prize] 2/16/77, folder 17 (Box box 5)
  - Lipmann, Fritz 7/14/77, folder 18 (Box box 5)
  - Woese, C. R. 8/12/77 - 9/30/77, folder 19 (Box box 5)
  - Grasso, Ella 4/11/80, folder 20 (Box box 5)
    Congratulatory letter from Connecticut Governor on award of Guggenheim award
  - Re, G.B. [Vatican] 12/12/86, folder 21 (Box box 5)
    Acknowledgment of letter sent by Dr. Morowitz
  - Altman, Sidney 11/9/86, folder 22 (Box box 5)
  - Snyder, Gary, folder 23 (Box box 5)
  - Invitation: Prime Minister India to Professor H. J. Moroquite (Morowitz) 12/1981, folder 1 (Box box 6)
  - Poem: "Mr. Swinburned Discovers TV" by Peg Bracken, folder 2 (Box box 6)
  - Le Ronde [Poems by Harold J. Morowitz], folder 3 (Box box 6)
  - Correspondence: Harold Morowitz/Michael McClure[poetry], folder 4 (Box box 6)
  - Murray Gellman birthday 1/27 - 28/89 5/27/88 and 11/28/88, folder 5 (Box box 6)
  - [Correspondence: Sagan to Morowitz re: Venus/Mars 10/12/66 and 10/21/66, folder 6 (Box box 6)
  - [News clippings: Arkansas Creation Trial 1 of 3] 12/8/81 -1/6/82, folder 7 (Box box 6)
  - [News clippings: Arkansas Creation Trial 2 of 3] 12/8/81 - 12/19/81, folder 8 (Box box 6)
  - [News clippings: Arkansas Creation Trial 3 of 3] 12/6/81 - 1/6/82, folder 9 (Box box 6)
  - Civil Liberties [ACLU, Louisiana creationism ] 5/6/82 - 7/17/85, folder 10 (Box box 6)
  - ACLU [Arkansas 1 of 2 ], folder 11 (Box box 6)
    Arkansas 1981 statute and Dr. Moskowitz's Q and A's regarding creationism
  - ACLU [Arkansas 2 of 2] 12/29/81 - 6/25/82, folder 12 (Box box 6)
    includes Morowitz's direct deposition
  - Gary Snyder 10/19/81 - 11/29/91, folder 13 (Box box 6)
  - The Ecology of Ego Niches, folder 14 (Box box 6)
    hand written draft manuscript
  - Post card: Beat Poets, folder 15 (Box box 6)
    picture post card
  - Arrow, Kenneth J. 4/30/91, folder 16 (Box box 6)
    confirm Morowitz acceptance of Editor-in-Chief of Complexity
  - Planetary Biology Subcommittee (NASA) 5/11/.66 - 1/14/70, folder 1 (Box box 7)
  - Re-Entry Talk - 9/26/93: Poem; "Biosphere II" 9/26/93, folder 2 (Box box 7)
  - Michael McClure: Minnie Mouse and th Tap Dancing Buddha, folder 3 (Box box 7)
  - Broadside: Gloaming", Michael McClure, folder 4 (Box box 7)
  - "Complexity" Editorial Board (1 of 2) 11/13/92 - 4/1994, folder 5 (Box box 7)
    includes letters regarding appointment of editorial board and litigation between SFI and Paragon Press regarding breach of contract to publish
  - "Complexity" Editorial Board 4/12/90 - 11/6/91, folder 6 (Box box 7)
    includes documentation of the birth of the "Complexity" journal and contract with Paragon Press
  - "Complexity" v. 3, no. 1, September/October 1997, folder 7 (Box box 7)
  - National Advisory Research Resources Council [pictures] 2/8-9/90 and 9/13 - 14/90, folder 8 (Box box 7)
  - Buckley, Will aim F. Jr. 2/4/82, folder 9 (Box box 7)
    letter from Buckley thanking Dr. Morowitz for a favorable article
  - [Yale] Encyclopedia of Scientific Concepts 3/27/89 - 11/12/90, folder 10A (Box box 7)
    letters regarding starting on the Encyclopedia
  - [Yale] Encyclopedia of Scientific Concepts 7/25/89 - 7/5/90, folder 10 B (Box box 7)
  - [Committee on Science and Human Values] 1 of 2 8/21/96 - 3/16/98, folder 11 (Box box 7)
  - [Committee on Science and Human Values] 2 of 2 1981 - 12/6/95, folder 12 (Box box 7)
  - [notes] for Facts of Life (1 of 2), folder 14 (Box box 7)
  - [notes] for Facts of Life [2 of 2], folder 15 (Box box 7)
  - H[ospital] P[ractices] (1 of 2) 3/6/83 - 2/1/95, folder 1 (Box box 8)
    fan mail regarding a column Dr Morowitz produced in Hospital Practices
  - H[ospital] P[ractices] (2 of 2) 12/31/74 - 10/14/82, folder 2 (Box box 8)
  - [Draft: The Kindly Dr. Guillotine], folder 3 (Box box 8)
  - Biomatrix 8/1991 and 1/1992, folder 4 (Box box 8)
  - Diffusion During Solvent Transport by Poiseuille Flow 1954, folder 5 (Box box 8)
  - Nutrient Transit Time Diversity: A Novel Measure of Ecological Organization and Stability 12/1995, folder 6 (Box box 8)
  - Competitive Exclusion: Application of A Biological Principle to Societies in Conflict, folder 7 (Box box 8)
  - Some Theoretical Consideration on the Use of Indicator Time - Concentration Curves in Hemodynamic Studies 1955, folder 8 (Box box 8)
    includes "A Proposed Method of Determining Arterial Venous Shunts" and Minutes of the Meeting N.Y. 3/13/55
  - Gerald Edelman 5/5/97, folder 9 (Box box 8)
    letter declines invitation on The Brain, The mind and The Classroom, suggests others to invite
  - Godel Numbers 2/27/67 and 4/18/67, folder 10 (Box box 8)
  - Lord Snow 2/20/70, folder 11 (Box box 8)
  - Journal of Irreproducible Results 2/1978, folder 12 (Box box 8)
  - Some Notes on the Problem of Uncertainty in Biological Measurements 3/1/66, folder 13 (Box box 8)
  - Taming Combinatorial Explosion 7/5/00, folder 14 (Box box 8)
  - Hospital Practice [source material and drafts], folder 15 (Box box 8)
  - The Mind, The Brain, and Complex Adaptive Systems 3/11/92 - 8/18/93, folder 16 (Box box 8)
    correspondence regarding The Mind, The Brain, and Complex Adaptive Systems, a conference inaugurating the Krasnow Institute
  - Publications 1/1968 - 1972, folder 17 (Box box 8)
    articles authored or co-authored by Dr. Morowitz
  - The Origin of Intermediary Metabolism 7/5/2000, folder 18 (Box box 8)
  - Self Replicating Machines 1962 - 4/21/64, folder 19 (Box box 8)
    Artificial Living Plants, 10/1956: Machine Models of Self Reproduction, 1962 both by Edward F. Moore
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 1, folder 1 (Box box 9)
    DRAFT
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 2, draft (Box BOX 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 3, folder 3 (Box box 9)
    draft
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 4, folder 4 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 5, folder 5 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 6, folder 6 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 7, folder 7 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 8, folder 8 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 9, folder 9 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 10, folder 10 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 11, folder 11 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 12, folder 12 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 13, folder 13 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 14, folder 14 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 15, folder 15 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 16, folder 16 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 17, folder 17 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 18, folder 18 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 19, folder 19 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 20, folder 20 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 21, folder 21 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 22, folder 22 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 23, folder 23 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 24, folder 24 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 25, folder 25 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 26, folder 26 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 27, folder 27 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 28, folder 28 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 29, folder 29 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 30, folder 30 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 31, folder 31 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 32, folder 32 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 33, folder 33 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 34, folder 34 (Box box 9)
  - [Emergences] - Chapter 35, folder 35 (Box box 9)
  - Biomatrix [meeting and Primer] 3/9/89 - 1/29/93, folder 36 (Box box 9)
  - Anti-Chaos, Teleology and Teilhard 5/1/90, folder 37 (Box box 9)
    A talk delivered by Professor Morowitz as part of a conference on Teilhard de Chardin; "Sharing the Great Work"
  - New Program at NSF 5/14/01, folder 1 (Box BOX 10)
    National Science Foundation, Biological Information Technology and Systems
  - [Research, Correspondence for Emergence 6/15/92 - 2/17/02, folder 2 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences Edited Papers, folder 3 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Preface, folder 4 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Contents, folder 5 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter 1, folder 6 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 2, folder 7 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 3, folder 8 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 4, folder 9 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 5, folder 10 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 6, folder 11 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 7, folder 12 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 8, folder 13 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 9, folder 14 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 10, folder 15 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 11, folder 16 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 12, folder 17 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 13, folder 18 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 14, folder 19 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 15, folder 20 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 16, folder 21 (Box box 10)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 17, folder 1 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 18, folder 2 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 19, folder 3 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 20, folder 4 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 21, folder 5 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 22, folder 6 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter 23, folder 7 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 24, folder 8 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 25, folder 9 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 26, folder 10 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 27, folder 11 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 28, folder 12 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 29, folder 13 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 30, folder 14 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 31, folder 15 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 32, folder 16 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 33, folder 17 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 34, folder 18 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 35, folder 19 (Box box 11)
  - Emergences - Chapter - 36, folder 20 (Box box 11)
  - Mycoplasma 1959 - 1/29/02, folder 21 (Box box 11)
  - Franklin, Harold [Mitchell Bio] 12/1968 - 1980, folder 1 (Box box 12)
    12 papers published by Harold Franklin
  - Paul Boyer [Mitchell bio] 10/1975 - 8/10/78, folder 2 (Box box 12)
    5 articles published by Paul Boyer
  - Lars Ernster 1969 - 1975, folder 3 (Box box 12)
    includes an undated Curriculum Vitae and an undated Bibliography
  - [Williams] 12/21/61 - 3/7/79, folder 4 (Box box 12)
    11 papers published by R.J.P. Williams; as well as correspondence from Morowitz to Williams and 3 articles by Peter Mitchell
  - [Biochemistry] 1979 - 6/28/84, folder 5 (Box box 12)
  - [E.C. Slater] 1953 - 6/17/80, includes a list of publications by Slater (Box box 12)
  - Kent Gabriel 10/30/79 - 6/25/80, folder 7 (Box box 12)
    Gabriel worked under Morowitz''s supervision
  - Protons - Onsager 1971, folder 8 (Box box 12)
    several undated papers included
  - [Research Proposal] 2/7/75 - 10/22/80, folder 9 (Box box 12)
  - [Publication List of Jennifer Moyle] 11/4/80, folder 10 (Box box 12)
  - [Protons, Electrons and Energy] 12/1975 -1980, folder 11 (Box box 12)
    6 articles on the subject and some handwritten notes
  - Sabbatical 80 - Misc. 1913 - 6/11/80, folder 12 (Box box 12)
  - [Oxidative phosoylations - notes, folder 13 (Box box 12)
  - [Letter on Entropy book] 1/6/81, folder 14 (Box box 12)
    book reviewed by Professor Morowitz
  - Hawaii Education (unpublished Intro to Merck's Medicine manual, popular edition), folder 16 (Box box 12)
  - {Misc.] 7/7/80 - 5/3/00, folder 17 (Box box 12)
    Includes: Correspondence between Bruce Weber and Professor Morowitz regarding a biography of Peter Mitchell; An Obituary article on Ernest Charles Pollard at Yale University; an invitation to participate on a New York Academy of Sciences workshop on toxicology; a letter certifying Professor Morowitz's selection as a Fellow at the John Simon Guggenheim memorial Foundation; and an undated article titled "Making Sense of Illness: Science, Society and Disease" by Robert O. Aronowitz
  - Deposition of Harold J. Morowitz (folder 1 of 2) 5/8/82, folder 1 (Box box 13)
    Senator Bill Keith, et al. plaintiffs vs. Louisiana Department of Education, et al. defendants
  - Deposition of Harold J. Morowitz (folder 2 of 2) 5/8/82, folder 2 (Box box 13)
  - [Patent on Making Negative Ions] 12/16/59 - 5/6/64, folder 3 (Box box 13)
    Professor Morowitz's invention was used by Puritron Corporation as a room refresher.
  - [The Fifth Keilin Memorial Lecture] 7/5/72, folder 4 (Box box 13)
    Electron Transfer and Oxidative Energy
  - [Bioenergetics] 8/28/54 - 2/10/81, folder 5 (Box box 13)
  - Wikstrom 1979, folder 6 (Box box 13)
    Proton Pumping Cytochrome c Oxidase
  - Van Dam 5/12/66, folder 7 (Box box 13)
    The Burst in ATP Synthesis Observed on Addition of ADP to Mitochondria
  - [Notes and Calculations], folder 8 (Box box 13)
    7 "blue books: one of which is labeled Notes for First Published Paper, another is notes on Absorbsition Effects in the Volume Irradiation of Microorganisms
  - [My Library], folder 9 (Box box 13)
    a short essay on a home laboratory, undated and unsigned
  - [Charts on a experiment from 2/2/61 - 2/8/61] 2/2/61 - 2/8/61, folder 10 (Box box 13)
  - [Labor Party] summer of 1944 -3/24/46, folder 11 (Box box 13)
    membership notes and description of Labor Party at yale University
  - [Essay on Ivan Pului], folder 12 (Box box 13)
    Ivan Pului born 2/2/1845, died 1/31/18, conducted experiments and published papers on cathode rays.
  - [Physics 32b Class Notes, Relativity Dynamics], folder 13 (Box box 13)
  - Alamethicin Paper 8/18/75 - 12/13/76, folder 14 (Box box 13)
  - [Misc Mitchell Biography], folder 15 (Box box 13)
  - [Mitchell Biography information] 1978 - 1982, folder 16 (Box box 13)
    Includes; "Pumps and Currents: A Biological Perspective by Franklyn M. Harold; Salt Dependence of the Electrical Potential at the Photsynthetic Membrane in Steady-State Light and Its Structural Consequence (12/21/81) by R. Tiemann and H.T. Witt; "Generation of Large and Active membrane Layers from Thylakoid Vesicles" (3/13/81) by H.T. Witt and D. Diore; "A Proton Motive Force Transducer and Its Role in Proton Pumps, Proton Engines, Tobacco Mosaic Virus Assembly and Hemoglobin Allosterism" (1/18/82) by A. Keith Dunker; "The Proton Gradient Across Mycoplasma Membranes" (1981) by Ulrich Schummer, Hans-Gerd Schiefer and Ursala Gerhadt; 'From Black-Box Biogenergetics to Molecular Mechanics:Vectorial Ligand-Conduction Mechanisms in Biochemistry" (1981) by Peter Mitchell; "Relation Between the Initial Kinetics of ATP Synthesis and of Conformational Changes in the Chloroplast ATPase Studied by External Pulses" (9/29/80) by E. Schlodder and H.T. Witt; " The Effective Proton Conductance of the Inner Membrane of Mitochondria from Brown Adipose Tissue' (1/4/77) by David G. Nicholls; "Aqueous Ion Channels" 12/15/80 by D.T.Edmonds; "Proton Pump Coupled to Cytochrome c Oxidace In Mitochondria" (3/17/77) M.K.F. Wikstrom; "The Mechanism of Energy Conservation and Tranduction by Mitochondrial Cytochrome c Oxidase" (4/12/77) by Marten K.F. Wiksrom and Herkko T. Saari; " Proton Semiconductors and Energy Transduction in Biological Systems" (1978) by Harold J. Morowitz; " The Mitchell Hypothesis: A Bibliography" (1975) by Michael G. Prisant
  - [Physics 100 class notes], folder 1 (Box box 13A)
    original hand written class notes
  - [Physics 100 class notes], folder 2 (Box box 13A)
    hand written class notes, reproduced for preservation
  - [Correspondence between Mitchell and Williams] 8/22/60 - 11/18/80, folder 1 (Box box 14)
  - Givens [Notes for Autobiography], folder 2 (Box box 14)
    draft of Professor Morowitz's Autobiography
  - [Autobiography], folder 3 (Box box 14)
  - Protons [folder 1 of 2] [Mitchell's Bio] 10/1947 - 1977, folder 4 (Box box 14)